<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>House of Black and White</title>
    <description>My blog</description>
    <link>http://blog.chriszimmerman.net</link>
    <atom:link href="http://blog.chriszimmerman.net/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
      <item>
        <title>Functions In JavaScript</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;functions-in-javascript&quot;&gt;Functions In Javascript&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At my job, I usually work on our C# backend, but I occasionally get to do some work in JavaScript. Not having nearly as much JavaScript experience as C# experience, I encounter things I don’t quite understand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One such thing is the number of ways in which a function can be declared. Here are several examples of ways I see functions written in JavaScript:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;#1)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;function isOdd(number) {
	return number % 2 == 1;
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;#2)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;var isOdd = function(number) {
	return number % 2 == 1;
};
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;#3)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;var isOdd = function isOdd(number) {
	return number % 2 == 1;
};
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s going on here? I’ll explain. But first, I’d like to talk about a few different features of JavaScript that will aid in understanding the differences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;first-class-functions&quot;&gt;First class functions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In JavaScript, functions are first-class citizens. This means that they can be assigned to values and passed around as values to other functions. This is pretty nifty. This is the reason why you’re even able to define a function like how the functions in examples #2 and #3 are defined. This concept is pretty standard in a lot of functional languages like Clojure, Haskell, and Elixir.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;function-declarations-vs-function-expressions&quot;&gt;Function declarations vs function expressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you define a function in the manner done in example #1, you are giving the function a name. This is an example of a &lt;em&gt;function declaration.&lt;/em&gt; The function is defined at parse time, which means that the function is available within all of the scope it’s declared in. This way of defining a function also gives the function a meaningful name in the call stack when trying to debug JavaScript code. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Examples #2 and #3 are examples of &lt;em&gt;function expressions&lt;/em&gt;. This means that the function is defined within an expression, usually a variable assignment expression. This results in the function being defined at run time. With function expressions, the function name is optional. However, if a name is not given to a function in a function expression, it will have no name in the stacktrace, which makes debugging difficult. Example #3 is an example of a &lt;em&gt;named function expression&lt;/em&gt;. Due to variable hoisting in JavaScript, this way of defining functions can potentially lead to a bad situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;hoisting&quot;&gt;Hoisting&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In JavaScript, variables are hoisted. This means that a variable can be declared anywhere within a given scope, but programs will execute as if the variable was declared right away at the top of the scope. In another language, such as C#, hoisting doesn’t exist, so the following code would be invalid:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;x = 7 + 3;
int x;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The C# compiler would inform you that there is an error with this code: x does not exist at the point of assigning it 7 + 3. However, a JavaScript analog such as the following code would be acceptable:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;x = 7 + 3;
var x;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In JavaScript, the variable &lt;code&gt;x&lt;/code&gt; would be assigned the value 10 and everything would be fine and dandy. The idiom in JavaScript is to declare all variables intended to be used within a given scope at the top of the scope. Coming from languages without hoisting and having a habit of declaring variables as close as I can to where they are used for the first time, I find this strange. But I get the idea of letting people know what they’re going to encounter in a function.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Going back to our examples above, here is a contrived instance where assigning the function to a variable would result in an error:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;function example(){
	return isOdd(7);

	var isOdd = function(number) {
		return number % 2 == 1;
	};
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I paste this in my browser console, I get the following error:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;TypeError: isOdd is not a function
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, this will execute without error, returning true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;function example(){
	return isOdd(7);

	function isOdd(number) {
		return number % 2 == 1;
	}
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t consider myself educated or experienced enough in JavaScript to say which of these methods is best for defining functions. At the very least, I would say using names with function expressions would be much better than not using names. That leaves the choice between function declarations and named function expressions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Feel free to leave a commment if you have an opinion on where one way would be used over another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;resources&quot;&gt;Resources&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://stackoverflow.com/questions/336859/var-functionname-function-vs-function-functionname&quot;&gt;Stack Overflow&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://programmers.stackexchange.com/questions/160732/function-declaration-as-var-instead-of-function&quot;&gt;More Stack Overflow&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/First-class_function&quot;&gt;Wikipedia - First Class Functions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/JavaScript/Reference/Statements/var&quot;&gt;var statements&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://kangax.github.io/nfe/&quot;&gt;Named function expressions demystified&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://javascriptweblog.wordpress.com/2010/07/06/function-declarations-vs-function-expressions/&quot;&gt;JavaScript, JavaScript…&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 25 Oct 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://blog.chriszimmerman.net//2015/10/25/Functions-In-JavaScript.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.chriszimmerman.net//2015/10/25/Functions-In-JavaScript.html</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Breaking Down Syntactic Sugar With The Saliva Of Curiosity - The foreach Statement In C#</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;breaking-down-syntactic-sugar-with-the-saliva-of-curiosity---the-foreach-statement-in-c&quot;&gt;Breaking Down Syntactic Sugar With The Saliva Of Curiosity - The foreach Statement In C#&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A feature of C# that I frequently use to process collections is the foreach statement. foreach is just syntactic sugar for making it easier to iterate over collections. I’d like to delve a bit into what’s going on under the hood. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;syntactic-sugar&quot;&gt;Syntactic sugar&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Syntactic sugar is syntax in a language that makes it easier to read. It makes the language “sweeter” to work with (ha!). While syntactic sugar is great for increasing readability in a language, it’s also good to know what’s going on underneath.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;foreach&quot;&gt;foreach&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;foreach allows you to pass in each individual element of a collection into a code block and execute that block of code with the element. In this way, you iterate over the collection. I’d like to show you a code sample to make what I mean a bit clearer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s take a look at the following method:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;	private void PrintNumbers()
	{
		IEnumerable&amp;lt;int&amp;gt; numbers = new List&amp;lt;int&amp;gt; { 1, 2, 3 };

		foreach(int number in numbers)
		{
			Console.WriteLine(String.Format(&quot;The number is {0}&quot;, number));
		}
	}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, a list of integers is declared. This is pretty straightforward. The next line is the start of the foreach statement. The format of a foreach statement is such:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;foreach(&lt;em&gt;type&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;element&lt;/em&gt; in &lt;em&gt;collection&lt;/em&gt;) &lt;em&gt;inner-statement&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;type&lt;/em&gt; declares the type of element being passed into the code block. Because we’re working with a list of integers, the type is int.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;element&lt;/em&gt; specifies the individual element that is used in the &lt;em&gt;inner-statement&lt;/em&gt;. The scope of the &lt;em&gt;element&lt;/em&gt; is only within the &lt;em&gt;inner-statement&lt;/em&gt; for the current iteration. For example, when the foreach block is executed the first time for the number 1, the variable “number” has a value of 1. The second time around, it has the value of 2. The third and last time around, it has the value of 3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;collection&lt;/em&gt; specifies the collection being iterated over. In this case, “numbers” is being passed in as the collection. In order for the statement to be syntactically valid, the type of &lt;em&gt;collection&lt;/em&gt; must implement the IEnumerable interface OR satisfy the following criteria:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1) &lt;em&gt;collection&lt;/em&gt; must have a method on it with the following signature: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;public T GetEnumerator()
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where T is a class type, struct type, or interface type.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2) The type T returned by GetEnumerator() must have a method with the following signature:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;public bool MoveNext()
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3) The type T returned by GetEnumerator() must have a property with the following signature: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;public [type of *collection*] Current
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;that allows the current value to be read.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;inner-statement&lt;/em&gt; is the statement (which can obviously be composed of multiple statements) that gets executed once for each element in the collection. In this case, the &lt;em&gt;inner-statement&lt;/em&gt; is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Console.WriteLine(String.Format(&quot;The number is {0}&quot;, number));
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When this method executes, the following output will be printed to the console:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;The number is 1
The number is 2
The number is 3
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;under-the-hood&quot;&gt;Under the hood&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But like I said before, this is syntactic sugar. What’s really going on? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The compiler will perform a transformation, or expansion, on the foreach statement. Whether or not &lt;em&gt;collection&lt;/em&gt; implements IEnumerable or meets the criteria previously mentioned will determine the type of expansion that takes place. Since the example is using a collection implementing IEnumerable, I will show that expansion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is what the method looks like after the expansion takes place:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;private void PrintNumbers()
{
	IEnumerable&amp;lt;int&amp;gt; numbers = new List&amp;lt;int&amp;gt; { 1, 2, 3 };

	IEnumerator enumerator = 
			((System.Collections.IEnumerable)(numbers)).GetEnumerator();
	try {
		while (enumerator.MoveNext()) {
			int element = (int)enumerator.Current;
			Console.WriteLine(String.Format(&quot;The number is {0}&quot;, element));
		}
	}
	finally {
		IDisposable disposable = enumerator as System.IDisposable;
		if (disposable != null) disposable.Dispose();
	}
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically, an enumerator is created that makes use of the methods on it that allow it to access each element in the collection. After the work has been done for a given element, it moves onto the next one. After all the elements have been iterated over, the enumerator is disposed of to free up memory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These two code blocks effectively achieve the same result. But wouldn’t you agree that the foreach statement pre-expansion looks a lot more pleasant and clearer? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We discussed how syntactic sugar makes it easier to read a given programming language. We also looked at the foreach statement in C# as an example of syntactic sugar and what really goes on under the hood. You can read more about foreach at &lt;a href=&quot;https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/aa664754%28v=vs.71%29.aspx&quot;&gt;Microsoft’s website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/aa664754%28v=vs.71%29.aspx&quot;&gt;Microsoft’s documentation on the foreach statement&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 30 Sep 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://blog.chriszimmerman.net//2015/09/30/ForEach.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.chriszimmerman.net//2015/09/30/ForEach.html</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>My Thoughts and Experiences on Pair Programming - Challenges</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;my-thoughts-and-experiences-on-pair-programming-part-3&quot;&gt;My Thoughts and Experiences on Pair Programming: Part 3&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the final post in a three part series. In &lt;a href=&quot;../10/My-Thoughts-And-Experiences-On-Pair-Programming-Intro.html&quot;&gt;part 1&lt;/a&gt; of this series, I gave an introduction to pair programming. In &lt;a href=&quot;../11/My-Thoughts-And-Experiences-On-Pair-Programming-Benefits.html&quot;&gt;part 2&lt;/a&gt;, I discussed the benefits of pair programming. I will now talk about the challenges of pair programming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;challenges&quot;&gt;Challenges&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pairing isn’t a silver bullet. Like anything, there are drawbacks that come with the advantages. There are also times when it’s better to not pair on work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tasks-not-meant-for-a-pair&quot;&gt;Tasks not meant for a pair&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are you making trivial changes to a configuration file? Are you tweaking the position of a UI control on a web page?  Are you doing a boring, repetitive task? If you said yes to any of these, you probably don’t need another person with you on these tasks. Some tasks are awful enough with just one person doing them and there is no benefit to subjecting another developer to the work. In fact, that other developer’s time is most likely better spent working on something else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At my old job, I worked on a WinForms app. Occasionally, we’d have to make changes to the UI. This involved using a designer in Visual Studio that didn’t *quite* show what would actually appear in the app, so we’d have to make our changes in the designer, compile, fire up the app, and go to the view to make sure the changes appeared how we intended them to appear. The cycle of tweak/compile/fire-up-app/go-to-view was several minutes. It was brutal. I paired on that task with somebody. It was totally unnecessary to have two people working on that task.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;staying-engaged&quot;&gt;Staying engaged&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s important that both people stay engaged on the task. Sometimes, a pair might have one person who has a more assertive personality and ends up hogging the keyboard, leaving the other person bored. Try to share duties. Practicing &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Test-driven_development&quot;&gt;Test-Driven Development&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://c2.com/cgi/wiki?PairProgrammingPingPongPattern&quot;&gt;ping-pong pairing&lt;/a&gt; help alleviate this issue. Each member of the pair doesn’t go too long without doing work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your pair looks bored, you can try asking an innocuous question without sounding accusatory like, “What do you think if we do X here?” That will usually get the other person back into the work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;friction&quot;&gt;Friction&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes you get stuck working with people you may disagree with professionally. Or even with people who are complete jerks. It happens. The best way to deal with this problem, in my experience, is to avoid it. Work with people who share your values. Work with people you enjoy working with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ask your manager to switch you to a team of people you want to work with. It might not always be able to happen, but you can still ask. Switch to another team at another company, if necessary. It sounds a little childish, but the friction of working directly with somebody who stresses you out all day can take its toll. And you don’t have to deal with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you can’t avoid working with them, try to communicate your issues with the person in a constructive way. Retrospectives are a good venue for this. Talking to the person one-on-one works as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a point in time where I dreaded every third day of work (assuming the pairing rotation remained constant) because it meant pairing with someone who didn’t share my code quality values. There was arguing about the worth of tests, whether or not to refactor code, whether or not to “just put this one quick hack in”, and a number of related topics. This took away from enjoyment of my job. Fortunately, the problem solved itself and the person moved to another team. My day-to-day became much better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;imposter-syndrome-ho&quot;&gt;Imposter syndrome, ho!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you’re working next to a person all day for 8 hours a day, they will see you make mistakes. This constant visibility into how you perform as a programmer can be stressful, especially if you’re somebody like me with imposter syndrome. My way of dealing with this is reminding myself that I’m a human being that makes mistakes. As long as I’m giving my best, that’s all that anyone can ask for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;its-exhausting&quot;&gt;It’s exhausting&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s hard to be on mentally all the time. Many people I know, myself included, have attested to being totally exhausted at the end of the day when we first started pairing. It takes a lot more to be involved all day with your pair, but I feel way more productive when with a pair than when not. Make sure to take breaks regularly. Get water and snacks. Go to the bathroom. Get up and stretch. Being on for extended periods of time can be unhealthy, so make sure you take breaks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;its-not-for-everybody&quot;&gt;It’s not for everybody&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some people have certain personality types that prevent them from being effective in a pairing environment. This does not make them a bad developer; they just operate more efficiently in a different setting. Some people need to be in their own zone to be effective at what they do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me personally, I find pairing beneficial mostly because I feel challenged when with another developer. I can’t be lazy. I can’t be on autopilot. I’m kept honest. I feel that this keeps me at the top of my game. I also get opportunities to share my knowledge with other developers. This results in a better team, a better community of developers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hopefully, my experiences have given you some insight into pair programming. If you want to read about some of my colleagues’ thoughts on pair programming, you can check out &lt;a href=&quot;http://anthonysciamanna.com/2015/04/18/ping-pong-pair-programming.html&quot;&gt;Anthony Sciamanna’s post on Ping Pong Pair Programming&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://dandonahue.net/2013/11/20/my-thoughts-on-pair-programming-intro.html&quot;&gt;Dan Donahue’s series of pair programming posts&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you would like to get started with pair programming, check out Avdi Grimm’s site &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.pairprogramwith.me/&quot;&gt;Pairprogramwith.me&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 12 Aug 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://blog.chriszimmerman.net//2015/08/12/My-Thoughts-And-Experiences-On-Pair-Programming-Challenges.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.chriszimmerman.net//2015/08/12/My-Thoughts-And-Experiences-On-Pair-Programming-Challenges.html</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>My Thoughts and Experiences on Pair Programming - Benefits</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;my-thoughts-and-experiences-on-pair-programming-part-2&quot;&gt;My Thoughts and Experiences on Pair Programming: Part 2&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;../10/My-Thoughts-And-Experiences-On-Pair-Programming-Intro.html&quot;&gt;part 1&lt;/a&gt; of my series, I gave an introduction to pair programming and discussed setting up an environment conducive to pair programming. I’ll now talk about the benefits of pair programming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;benefits&quot;&gt;Benefits&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;no-single-point-of-failure&quot;&gt;No single point of failure&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I said, there are many benefits to pair programming. For starters, because two developers are actively working on solving a problem or writing a feature, both devs will have the knowledge of the work in their heads. This results in redundancy on the team. There is no “The Guy” on the team who, should they get hit by a bus, go on vacation, or decide to quit, would end up screwing the team over (whether intentionally or unintentionally). There is no single point of failure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;collaboration-and-improved-design&quot;&gt;Collaboration and improved design&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When two brains are working on writing software, both are giving input and critique to the design of the software being written. Pairing is a great vessel for collaboration. With pairing, you get multiple perspectives of a problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pairing is also great for experimentation. One person in the pair can propose an experimental idea to try and the other can critique and improve it. If there are feelings that the pair is going too far down a rabbit hole, the experiment can be aborted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mentoring&quot;&gt;Mentoring&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have had the extreme pleasure of working with awesome, intelligent people who have mentored me over the past few years. In my experience, the best way to learn is by doing. When I started my first job, my pair would explain something new to me then let me try doing the work myself, offering me help if I needed it. I think this is a great way to have the struggle that leads to growth while having help nearby if it’s truly needed. When a junior and senior developer pair, it’s usually very beneficial for the junior. It can be a little stressful for the senior since they have to keep on task while making sure the junior doesn’t stray too far off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find pairing is most optimal for both people in the pair when they 1) have a similar skill level or 2) have a similar level of familiarity with the codebase. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At my first job, I was not only new to the codebase, but new to professional software development altogether. All of the other devs on the team had experience and had worked in the codebase for some time. When I paired, the other dev usually knew right where to go to do work for a given problem. I just went along because it would have slowed us down if I had taken the time to muck through the codebase to find what we needed to change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About six months into it, another developer joined our team. He had a few more years of experience than I, but he was unfamiliar with the codebase. Since we both had a degree of unfamiliarity, we were able to explore the codebase together. There was no person with all of the answers right there solving the problem for us. This was great because we were able to explore the codebase and grow together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;being-kept-on-track&quot;&gt;Being kept on track&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having another human being present is great for keeping yourself on track. Because someone else is right there, you feel guilty for goofing off on Reddit or Hacker News, so you’re kept on task. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also mean this in a benign way. Having a pair present is great for preventing rabbit-holes that are normally traversed when a developer is working by themself. Your pair is there to catch you when you fall. Stupid things like syntax errors are quickly found and resolved with another set of eyes on the code being written. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;growth-and-challenge&quot;&gt;Growth and challenge&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can say that I’m always challenged when pairing with someone (unless we’re stuck doing a menial or tedious task). I might have to explain work that was done on a task to a newcomer. It might be the other way around; I might have to get myself up to speed on work that I was not involved in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have to be way more into it mentally than if I were by myself because I don’t want to let my pair down. Hands down, this has made me a better software developer. When pairing, I’m constantly pushed and I’m cool with that. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;gelling&quot;&gt;Gelling&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I consider many of the people I have paired with over the years good friends. As you work together with the people you pair with, you get to know them really well and gel. I feel that a team works much better if they get along really well and trust each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;part-3&quot;&gt;Part 3&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;../12/My-Thoughts-And-Experiences-On-Pair-Programming-Challenges.html&quot;&gt;part 3&lt;/a&gt; I discuss the challenges of pair programming.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 11 Aug 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://blog.chriszimmerman.net//2015/08/11/My-Thoughts-And-Experiences-On-Pair-Programming-Benefits.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.chriszimmerman.net//2015/08/11/My-Thoughts-And-Experiences-On-Pair-Programming-Benefits.html</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>My Thoughts and Experiences on Pair Programming - Intro</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Note: This is part one of a three part series. You can find &lt;a href=&quot;../11/My-Thoughts-And-Experiences-On-Pair-Programming-Benefits.html&quot;&gt;part 2&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;../12/My-Thoughts-And-Experiences-On-Pair-Programming-Challenges.html&quot;&gt;part 3&lt;/a&gt; here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;my-thoughts-and-experiences-on-pair-programming-part-1&quot;&gt;My Thoughts and Experiences on Pair Programming: Part 1&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the time of writing this post, I have about 3.5 years of experience as a professional software developer. For the majority of my career, I have worked in places that have done pair programming, or pairing. Overall, I have had positive experiences with pairing. I wish to speak about my experiences with pair programming, explaining some of the benefits and difficulties that come with the practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-pair-programming&quot;&gt;What is pair programming?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pair programming is when two developers actively work together on writing a piece of software at the same time. Pairing can be done with two developers sitting at the same physical location, or it can be done remotely. Pair programming yields a number of great benefits, including real-time code reviews and increased knowledge transfer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;pair-switching&quot;&gt;Pair switching&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When developers pair program, the same developers don’t stay together all the time (unless the team consists of two developers). By switching pairs, developers get to work with everybody else on the team and get exposed to other work. My experience with pair switching has been the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Devs A and B have been working on task 1 and Devs C and D have been working on task 2. The pairs have worked on their respective tasks for one pairing session, which lasts for a given period of time that is agreed upon by the team. I have had pairing sessions last for a whole day, a half day, or two hours. After a session, the pairs will switch up. Devs A and C will work on task 1 and devs B and D will work on task 2. Dev A brings Dev C up to task on the work that has been done by devs A and B. Dev D will bring Dev B up to speed on what has been done by devs C and D for task 2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The devs will pair for another session. Afterward, the developer who most recently came onto the task will stay on while the other person switches off. Because Dev A was on task 1 longer than Dev C, Dev A will switch off and Dev C will bring Dev D up to speed on task 1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is just an example of how to pair switch. Sometimes the same people will end up pairing together often or certain people will gravitate toward certain tasks. I think it’s good to work with everyone on your team and get exposed to a variety of work. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-driver-and-navigator-roles&quot;&gt;The driver and navigator roles&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While pairing, at any given time, one developer plays the role of driver. This is the person actually writing code. Their concern is with the immediate task at hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other developer plays the role of navigator. The navigator keeps a higher level picture of the work in their head. They think about the current task as well as what has been done and what has yet to be done. During a pairing session, developers will frequently exchange these roles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-odd-person&quot;&gt;The odd person&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you have an odd number of developers on your team, there will be a person left over after devs pair up. This person is referred to the “odd person.” At one job, we didn’t allow the odd person to push any production code without someone else reviewing it. Obviously, you can’t just have a dev sitting around doing nothing. In my experience, this person usually worked on investigations or tooling for the team. In other places, the odd person was allowed to push production code as long as it was code reviewed by somebody else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;setting-up-an-environment-conducive-to-effective-pairing&quot;&gt;Setting up an environment conducive to effective pairing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to pair effectively, developers need to have the proper environment set up. This means having both 1) a physical environment (chairs, desks, keyboards, mice, etc.) and 2) a development environment (IDEs, editors, tools, etc.) where both developers can work comfortably. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-desk&quot;&gt;The desk&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, let’s talk about the desk. Physical comfort is important. The developers should be able to sit at the desk comfortably without getting in each other’s space. Wide rectangular desks work well. I have had the displeasure of pairing at L-shaped corner desks. They are horrible. One person sits comfortably in the middle of the L while the other person has to sit uncomfortably at the edge of the L at an angle to the desk. It’s the worst. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my experience, the desk has a monitor, mouse, and keyboard for each developer. The desk should be large enough so that all of these things can fit comfortably. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each dev having their own monitor, mouse, and keyboard allows them to easily jump in and contribute. I have heard of places where the keyboard, mouse, and monitor are shared, but I have not worked that way personally. I have also heard of places that will have the monitors face opposite directions, resulting in the developers facing each other. I hear this lends to having better conversations, but again, I don’t have any personal experience with this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../../../images/8-3-15/dan.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;My pairing desk at eMoney Advisor along with my coworker Dan Donahue&quot; title=&quot;My pairing desk at eMoney Advisor along with my coworker Dan Donahue&quot; /&gt;
My pairing desk at eMoney along with my coworker &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dandonahue.net&quot;&gt;Dan Donahue&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;machines&quot;&gt;Machines&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At my current job, I have &lt;em&gt;my&lt;/em&gt; machine. I log into it with &lt;em&gt;my&lt;/em&gt; credentials and I’m responsible for what happens with that machine. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I dislike this. It encourages thinking in terms of the individual instead of in terms of the pair. Or in terms of the team, for that matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At my previous job, I had my own network account, but my team had a set of team machines. On each machine, we created a local team account with the proper permissions to get work done. We agreed as a team on a particular setup for the machines so that no matter what machine you worked on, it was indistinguishable from any of the other machines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having machines with the same setup saves a lot of headaches because you don’t have to worry about which tools, packages, etc. are installed on a given machine. Another advantage of having team machines is that if a pair ends the day in the middle of work that is not ready to be committed, it’s easy to jump back into it the next day and not have to worry about things like if a member of the pair will be out the next day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tools&quot;&gt;Tools&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When devs pair, they’ll be using the same tools. Examples of tools are text editors, IDEs, plugins, and keyboard configurations. It’s best to come to some sort of agreement on which tools to use. I’ve been on teams that come of with working agreements for tools and it worked out well when the team members respect the working agreements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Going back to the comfort motif, make sure to decide on tools that most, if not all, members of the team are comfortable using. Because I’m such a nice dude, I’m willing to concede on certain things to make the other person more comfortable. For example, I like to use the VSVim plugin for Visual Studio. I pair with people who dislike using vim, so I’ll disable the plugin when I pair with them as to not hamper their productivity. While I feel vim is great for text editing (and you should totally use it!), I can get by without it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;part-2&quot;&gt;Part 2&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;../11/My-Thoughts-And-Experiences-On-Pair-Programming-Benefits.html&quot;&gt;part 2&lt;/a&gt; I talk about the benefits of pair programming.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 10 Aug 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://blog.chriszimmerman.net//2015/08/10/My-Thoughts-And-Experiences-On-Pair-Programming-Intro.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.chriszimmerman.net//2015/08/10/My-Thoughts-And-Experiences-On-Pair-Programming-Intro.html</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Equality Comparison In JavaScript</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;equality-comparison-in-javascript&quot;&gt;Equality Comparison In JavaScript&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s talk about something not fun: equality comparison in JavaScript. In most languages, operators for checking equality and inequality between two values exist. They usually are == and !=, respectively. JavaScript has these operators as well, but they come with a not fun surprise. In addition to performing comparison, these operators perform type coercion in order to match the types if they are different. The tricky thing is that sometimes JavaScript coerces types to values that you wouldn’t expect. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;truthy-and-falsy-values&quot;&gt;Truthy and Falsy Values&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When comparing two different values that are of different types, JavaScript will coerce these values into booleans when == and != are used. What makes this weird is that values in JavaScript can be ‘truthy’ or ‘falsy’. For example, if you opened up a console in your browser and typed the following statement:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;0 == false;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You would get &lt;code&gt;true&lt;/code&gt; as a result. In JavaScript, the number 0 is a falsy value. Falsy values evaluate to false when treated as boolean values. After the type coercion, we have the following statement:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;false == false;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;which is a true statement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In JavaScript, the following values are falsy:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;0
&#39;&#39; and &quot;&quot; (the empty string)
null
undefined
false
NaN (not a number)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Truthy values evaluate to true when coerced into booleans. Examples of truthy values are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;3
&quot;Borat&quot;
true
{ location: &quot;Minnesota&quot;, population: 12000000 }
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;just-use--and-&quot;&gt;Just Use === and !==&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I probably should have said this right off the bat:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Don’t ever use the == and != operators when writing JavaScript code.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No good will come of this. Whenever encountering code that uses these operators, unnecessary mental energy must be expended thinking about the possibility of the gotchas that these operators bring. Instead, just use these operators:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;===
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;!==
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are known as the strict equality and strict inequality operators, respectively. They behave like how == and != operators work in most other languages. Unlike == and !=, if two values of different types are being compared, no type coercion will occur and the expression will evaluate to false.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In JavaScript, use === and !== for comparision. Your brain (and other brains!) will thank you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://stackoverflow.com/questions/359494/does-it-matter-which-equals-operator-vs-i-use-in-javascript-comparisons&quot;&gt;StackOverflow&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/JavaScript/Reference/Operators/Comparison_Operators&quot;&gt;Comparison Operators&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/JavaScript/Equality_comparisons_and_sameness&quot;&gt;Comparison and Sameness&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jul 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://blog.chriszimmerman.net//2015/07/22/Equality-Comparison-In-JavaScript.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.chriszimmerman.net//2015/07/22/Equality-Comparison-In-JavaScript.html</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Javascript - call() and apply()</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;javascript---call-and-apply&quot;&gt;Javascript - call() and apply()&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I first encountered the call() and apply() functions in Javascript, I had difficulty wrapping my head around how they worked. I also wasn’t really sure what practical purpose they served. I’m going to explain how these two functions work and what they are used for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;call&quot;&gt;call()&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;call() is a function that allows you to execute a function while specifying your own context in which it will run. For example, let’s say we had the following function:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;function printPokemonInfo() {
	alert(this.name + &#39; is Pokemon #&#39; + this.number + &#39; and is a &#39; + this.type + &#39; type.&#39;);
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This function will print out information about a Pokemon in an alert window. However, something is amiss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The function is accessing properties off of &lt;code&gt;this&lt;/code&gt; to display the information. But no Pokemon object is being passed in. And no, this function is not part of an object that contains the properties being accessed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As it is, this function will execute with all of the accessed values being undefined, which is pretty useless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s also say I have the following variable declared:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;var pokemon = { number: &#39;001&#39;, name: &#39;Bulbasaur&#39;, type: &#39;Grass&#39; };
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can make this function work by calling the call() function like so:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;printPokemonInfo.call(pokemon);
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I get the expected output:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Bulbasaur is Pokemon #001 and is a Grass type.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why on earth would you want to do this? What practical purpose does this serve?  Why not just make the pokemon an argument of the function? I’ll explain shortly. But first, I want to also show you apply().&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;apply&quot;&gt;apply()&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s take the above example where we use call and replace call with apply:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;printPokemonInfo.apply(pokemon);
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We get the exact same result as before. Okay, there must be a difference between the two. Otherwise, why have two different things that do the same thing?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both call() and apply() take additional arguments that are optional. call() takes a list of optional arguments to pass into the function, whereas apply() takes a single array of arguments to pass in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will modify my function to demonstrate how additional arguments work for call():&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;function printPokemonInfo(times, adjective) {
	for(var i = 0; i &amp;lt; times; i++){
		alert(this.name + &#39; is Pokemon #&#39; + this.number + &#39; and is a &#39; + this.type + &#39; type. It is &#39; + adjective + &#39;.&#39; );
	}
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I’ll make the following call:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;printPokemonInfo.call(pokemon, 3, &#39;cool&#39;);
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I will get three alert dialogs that say:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Bulbasaur is Pokemon #001 and is a Grass type. It is cool.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I said before, apply() only takes an array of arguments as an additional argument. So I would have to slightly change what I’m passing in to apply():&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;printPokemonInfo.apply(pokemon, [3, &#39;cool&#39;]);
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I get the same result. I get three alert dialogs that say:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Bulbasaur is Pokemon #001 and is a Grass type. It is cool.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;practical-applications&quot;&gt;Practical Applications&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A great practical purpose of using call() and apply() is to make use of faking subclassing in JavaScript. Although JavaScript is a prototype-based language and not a classical one, you can still perform a facsimile of inheritance by using call() or apply().&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s say I have the following constructor:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;var Person = function(firstName, lastName) {
	this.firstName = firstName;
	this.lastName = lastName;
};
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This constructor for my Person object takes in two parameters, firstName and lastName. Let’s say I wanted to ‘subclass’ and reuse this constructor for objects that I want to have the same properties as Person objects. I have two ‘subclasses’, Student and Professor, that make use of the Person constructor code so I don’t have to write it again:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;var Student = function(firstName, lastName, major) {
	Person.call(this, firstName, lastName);
	this.major = major;
};

var Professor = function(firstName, lastName, department) {
	Person.apply(this, [firstName, lastName]);
	this.department = department;
};
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the following code, I get an object with a firstName and lastName property:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;var joe = new Person(&#39;Joe&#39;, &#39;Smith&#39;);
//	{ firstName: &quot;Joe&quot;, lastName: &quot;Smith&quot; }
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the following code, I get an object with a firstName, lastName, and department property:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;var doc = new Professor(&#39;Richard&#39;, &#39;Stallman&#39;, &#39;Computer Science&#39;);
//	{ firstName: &quot;Richard&quot;, lastName: &quot;Stallman&quot;, department: &quot;Computer Science&quot; }
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Student class works similarly:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;var jimmy = new Student(&#39;Jimmy&#39;, &#39;Jones&#39;, &#39;Psychology&#39;);
//	{ firstName: &quot;Jimmy&quot;, lastName: &quot;Jones&quot;, major: &quot;Psychology&quot; }
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The call() and apply() functions allow you to specify a context for a given function, along with any parameters needed for that function. These functions provide a great way to emulate subclassing in JavaScript.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jun 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://blog.chriszimmerman.net//2015/06/21/Call-And-Apply.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.chriszimmerman.net//2015/06/21/Call-And-Apply.html</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A Month With Python</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;a-month-with-python&quot;&gt;A Month With Python&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, I attended an exceptional philly.rb meetup where two talks were presented. One was on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.slideshare.net/WilliamJeffries1/civic-hacking-on-rails&quot;&gt;civic hacking&lt;/a&gt; and one was on &lt;a href=&quot;http://lanyrd.com/2015/mwrc/sdkmkc/#link-cbfhz&quot;&gt;language exploration&lt;/a&gt;. The talk on language exploration, titled “Make up your own ‘Hello, world!’”, inspired me to take a short-to-medium-term look into a new language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Justin Campbell’s talk, he discusses the importance and benefits of learning new languages. Here’s the gist: take up a new language and implement a nontrivial-yet-not-crazily-complex project. Try to embrace the idioms of the language while implementing your project so that you expand your mind, gain new perspective, and bring what you’ve learned back into the languages you currently work in. Justin’s ‘Hello world’ of choice is a URL shortener. It’s a nontrivial project and ensures that you’ll be using a not insignificant portion of the language’s features in order to implement it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided to try this idea and timebox learning a new language to a month. The language I chose: Python. My version of ‘Hello, world!’: a &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sudoku&quot;&gt;sudoku&lt;/a&gt; solver. With a sudoku solver, you can learn how to get user input in several ways: from a file, from them typing it in by hand, from a web form. Once you get the input, you need to parse and validate the puzzle to see if it’s already invalid. If not, you can attempt to solve it. As far as solving goes, I kept my solver simple and used a brute force algorithm to solve the puzzle. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;motivation&quot;&gt;Motivation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I regard Python and Ruby as the Pepsi and Coke of dynamically typed languages. They’re pretty similar, or so I’ve heard. Before taking this journey, I only knew Ruby. I have used Ruby mostly as a scripting language to help automate tasks at my previous job. Other than that, I like to work on small side projects in Ruby. I find Ruby very enjoyable to work in. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I wanted to make sure I wasn’t missing out on anything. I heard that Python had fantastic libraries like SciPy and NumPy for support in science and math-related tasks. After attending this talk, I saw this as a great opportunity to get a taste for a language without heavily investing in it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;projects&quot;&gt;Project(s)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For my first week or so with Python, I went through a good deal of &lt;a href=&quot;https://automatetheboringstuff.com/&quot;&gt;Automating the Boring Stuff With Python&lt;/a&gt; by Al Sweigart. Because of my Ruby background, I didn’t find much in Python too unfamiliar. Going through this book got my head around fundamentals of Python like how to name variables/classes/methods and basic syntax. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After getting my feet wet, I moved on to writing a sudoku solver that is (mostly) unit tested and is capable of solving 9 by 9 sudoku puzzles. In doing this, I gained some experience with using Python’s unittest library. Here is an example of a unit test written in Python:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;class SudokuPuzzleSolverTest(unittest.TestCase):

	def test_is_valid(self):
		puzzle = [
			[
				Square(1,1,1,1),
				Square(4,1,2,1),
				Square(3,1,3,2),
				Square(2,1,4,2)
			],
			[
				Square(3,2,1,1),
				Square(2,2,2,1),
				Square(4,2,3,2),
				Square(1,2,4,2)
			],
			[
				Square(4,3,1,3),
				Square(1,3,2,3),
				Square(2,3,3,4),
				Square(3,3,4,4)
			],
			[
				Square(2,4,1,3),
				Square(3,4,2,3),
				Square(1,4,3,4),
				Square(4,4,4,4)
			]
		]
solver = Solver()
self.assertTrue(solver.is_valid(puzzle))
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my project, I represent a sudoku puzzle as a list of lists of &lt;code&gt;Square&lt;/code&gt; objects. Here is my Square class:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;class Square(object):
	def __init__(self, number, row, column, block):
		self.number = number
		self.row = row 
		self.column = column 
		self.block = block

	def __eq__(self, other):
		return (isinstance(other, self.__class__)
				and self.__dict__ == other.__dict__)

	def __hash__(self):
		return int(str(self.number) + str(self.row) + str(self.column) + str(self.block))
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My solution has two objects: a &lt;code&gt;FileReader&lt;/code&gt; and a &lt;code&gt;Solver&lt;/code&gt;. The responsibility of the &lt;code&gt;FileReader&lt;/code&gt; object is to read the contents of a file and convert it into my representation of a sudoku puzzle. An example file looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;_ 4 3 9 _ _ 2 _ 5
8 _ 5 _ 7 _ 6 _ _
6 _ _ 5 _ _ 3 _ 9
_ _ 2 _ 8 _ _ _ _
_ 3 _ 2 5 4 _ 1 _
_ _ _ _ 1 _ 9 _ _
2 _ 9 _ _ 5 _ _ 8
_ _ 4 _ 2 _ 5 _ 7
1 _ 6 _ _ 7 4 2 _
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One method reads the file, getting a list of strings as output. Another method sanitizes that list of strings, extracts the numbers (or blanks) and converts them into sudoku &lt;code&gt;Square&lt;/code&gt; objects. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The responsibility of the &lt;code&gt;Solver&lt;/code&gt; class is to take that list of lists and 1) make sure that the puzzle is even solvable with the squares that are already filled in and 2) to find the solution if one can be found. As said before, I use a &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sudoku_solving_algorithms#Backtracking&quot;&gt;brute force algorithm&lt;/a&gt; to solve the puzzle. Once the puzzle is solved, the solution is printed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;impressions-of-python&quot;&gt;Impressions of Python&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I expected, I found Python very similar to Ruby. I didn’t discover anything mind-blowing like I most likely would have if I had tried something unfamiliar, like ELM, Swift, or Haskell. I found this to be a bummer, as one of the potential benefits of learning a new programming language is having your brain expanded in different ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like Python. But I like Ruby better. Mostly due to personal preferences, I suppose. Ruby actually has private methods. Python has no concept of privateness. I like chaining methods. I prefer &lt;code&gt;&quot;kitties&quot;.upcase.reverse.length&lt;/code&gt; over &lt;code&gt;len(&quot;kitties&quot;.upper()[::-1])&lt;/code&gt;. If I had a job where I wrote in Python, I wouldn’t be upset. But Ruby would be a much more preferable alternative. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m glad that I did this exercise, even if I found out that Python isn’t a language that I would like to pursue further at this time. Justin has a really great way for looking into new programming languages and I’m glad that I tried his idea. I highly recommend taking a similar approach for learning a new programming language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can find the source code for my solver &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/chriszimmerman/python_month/tree/master/sudoku&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://lanyrd.com/2015/mwrc/sdkmkc/#link-cbfhz&quot;&gt;Make Up Your Own ‘Hello, World!’&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://automatetheboringstuff.com/&quot;&gt;Automating the Boring Stuff With Python&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 31 May 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://blog.chriszimmerman.net//2015/05/31/A-Month-With-Python.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.chriszimmerman.net//2015/05/31/A-Month-With-Python.html</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Game Programming C# With XNA</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;game-programming-in-c-with-xna&quot;&gt;Game Programming in C# With XNA&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every year for the past few years, I’ve been going to PAX East, an annual video game convention in Boston. Every time, I get inspired to make video games, but never actually act on that inspiration. I don’t know if it’s due to A) a lack of original ideas, B) poor artistic skill, C) laziness, or D) all of the above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shortly after my trip to PAX East in March of this year, I started a &lt;a href=&quot;https://class.coursera.org/gameprogramming-002&quot;&gt;Coursera class&lt;/a&gt; about game programming in C#. In this class, I learned about writing C# games using Microsoft’s XNA Framework. The class was aimed at people who have never done programming before. However, I already knew the language features of C# taught in the class, so I was able to focus on learning about XNA objects and APIs, as well as game-programming-specific concepts like collision detection and calculating sprite velocities. A few of the games I created were a simple blackjack game and a game where you are a hamburger that shoots french fries at teddy bears while they bounce around and shoot mini teddy bears at you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would like to share what I learned in the course from the XNA and game development perspective. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-xna-framework&quot;&gt;The XNA Framework&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Microsoft’s XNA &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/download/details.aspx?id=20914&quot;&gt;XNA’s Not Acronymed&lt;/a&gt; Framework contains objects that make it relatively easy to create video games. There are objects for handling keyboard and mouse input, getting mouse state, drawing sprites on the screen, and working with sprite movement, to name a few.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;Mouse&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;MouseState&lt;/code&gt; classes allow you to get information about mouse position and button state. The &lt;code&gt;Texture2D&lt;/code&gt; class contains information related to a grid of pixels that compose a sprite. The &lt;code&gt;Rectangle&lt;/code&gt; class allows you to access information about the rectangle that represents the sprite, such as length, width, X position, Y, position, upper left corner, and so on. The &lt;code&gt;Vector2&lt;/code&gt; object is a commonly used object that defines a vector used in game physics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;fundamental-game-concepts&quot;&gt;Fundamental Game Concepts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-game-loop&quot;&gt;The Game Loop&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most fundamental concepts in game programming is the game loop. The game loop constantly runs, checking for user input and updating the environment. For example, the game loop may have code to draw a bullet sprite from a spaceship when the left mouse button is pressed. There may be code to check for when a bullet sprite comes into contact with an alien sprite and play an explosion animation when that occurs. The game loop repeats indefinitely until the game is terminated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, the game loop might look something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;while(gameIsRunning){
	CheckForInputFromUser();
	UpdateInternalGameState();
	UpdateVisualsForPlayer();
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following code sample is from a simplified blackjack game I wrote for an assignment:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;protected override void Update(GameTime gameTime)
{
	MouseState mouseState = Mouse.GetState();
	foreach(var menuButton in menuButtons){
		if(currentState == GameState.WaitingForPlayer || currentState == GameState.DisplayingHandResults){
			menuButton.Update(mouseState);
		}
	}

	switch(currentState){
		case GameState.PlayerHitting:
			PlayerHit();
			break;
		case GameState.WaitingForDealer:
			DealerTurn();
			break;
		case GameState.DealerHitting:
			DealerHit();
			break;
		case GameState.CheckingHandOver:
			CheckHandOver();
			break;
		case GameState.DisplayingHandResults:
			break;
		case GameState.Exiting:
			Exit();
			break;
		default:
			break;
	}

	base.Update(gameTime);
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every time this method executes (which is happening very often), it’s getting information about the mouse which is stored in &lt;code&gt;mouseState&lt;/code&gt;. This includes the X and Y position of the cursor, which button(s) are pressed, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The blackjack game was designed around a &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Deterministic_finite_automaton&quot;&gt;DFA&lt;/a&gt;, the states of which are determined by each of the &lt;code&gt;GameState&lt;/code&gt; enum values. If the game is in either of the two states where player input is awaited (&lt;code&gt;GameState.WaitingForPlayer&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;GameState.DisplayingHandResults&lt;/code&gt;), it’s going to call the &lt;code&gt;Update&lt;/code&gt; method on each menu button within the game, which will check if any of the buttons (such as the Hit, Stand, or Quit buttons) have been clicked. If the game is not in any of those states, it’s going to go through the switch statement and execute the appropriate code which represents the DFA transition. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sprites&quot;&gt;Sprites&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2D game programming, all objects in the world are displayed as sprites. Player characters, enemies the player fights, items the player gets, and other objects and entities in the world are displayed as sprites. Sprites are rectangles of varying sizes that have images placed on them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../../../images/4-30-15/explosion.png&quot; alt=&quot;Explosion spritesheet&quot; title=&quot;An explosion spritesheet&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An explosion spritesheet containing the sprites for an animation. Taken from Dr. Tim “Dr. T” Chamillard’s course Beginning Game Programming With C#&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sprites have a length and width, as well as a position. The position is usually the upper left corner of the sprite, but in some situations, the center point of the sprite is used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;collision-detection&quot;&gt;Collision Detection&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order for games to be interesting, things need to happen when sprites interact with each other. Collision detection is a term used to describe when the game checks for when sprites intersect each other and what to do when that happens. In Super Mario Bros, if Mario walks into a goomba, he shrinks if he’s big or he dies if he’s small. However, if he jumps on top of the goomba, he’ll bounce back up and get points. The goomba will also be dead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../../../images/4-30-15/collision.png&quot; alt=&quot;Collision detection&quot; title=&quot;Collision detection&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order for sprites to move, they usually have a velocity that dictates which direction they move and how fast, in terms of pixels per update cycle. By making a &lt;code&gt;Vector2&lt;/code&gt; a property of a game object, you can store information about the object’s velocity. You can pass in an X speed and a Y speed for the velocity. A positive X value indicates how many pixels to the right per update cycle you want the sprite to move. A negative X value is the same thing, except moving to the left instead of the right. A positive Y value incidates how many pixels down per update cycle you want the sprite to move, while a negative Y value is how many pixels up you want it to move. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the image below, the blue square has an X speed of 4 and a Y speed of zero. It’s moving to the right at 4 pixels per cycle and it’s not moving up or down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../../../images/4-30-15/vectors.png&quot; alt=&quot;Sprite velocity&quot; title=&quot;Sprite velocity&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;removing-unused-resources&quot;&gt;Removing Unused Resources&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a game where many objects appear on the screen, something must be done about those objects once they are off screen. The resources for those objects must be freed or else the game will suffer performance degredation. The computer might also run out of memory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A simple way of doing this is having an &lt;code&gt;IsActive&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;ReadyForDisposal&lt;/code&gt; property on each object and set it to the appropriate value when it’s on or off screen. When the game updates, check for any unused resources lingering around and delete them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;criticism&quot;&gt;Criticism&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing I dislike about game programming in XNA is that it seems difficult to do great OO programming. In the games I’ve done, I work out of a giant &lt;code&gt;Game&lt;/code&gt; class. I have other classes for objects in my games, but it seems like a lot of stuff exists in my &lt;code&gt;Game&lt;/code&gt; class. &lt;code&gt;Game&lt;/code&gt; has its fingers in a lot of pies with having &lt;code&gt;Initialize(), LoadContent(), UnloadContent(), Update(),&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;Draw()&lt;/code&gt; methods. I feel like it has too much responsibility. I suppose the game needs to simultaneously update the visuals of the game and the unseen logic, but I feel like that violates the Single Responsibility Principle because I see those two tings as two different responsibilities. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have talked about some basic 2D game development concepts, as well as some of the XNA Framework’s API. Using the knowledge I’ve learned from the course, I’ve been able to make a few simple games that are fun to play. If you’ve ever wanted to make a video game, I encourage checking out this course. Get out there and have some fun!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;resources&quot;&gt;Resources&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://class.coursera.org/gameprogramming-002&quot;&gt;Coursera - Game Programming in C#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/download/details.aspx?id=20914&quot;&gt;Microsoft XNA&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 30 Apr 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://blog.chriszimmerman.net//2015/04/30/Game-Programming-In-C%23-With-XNA.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.chriszimmerman.net//2015/04/30/Game-Programming-In-C%23-With-XNA.html</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Retrospectives - A Tool for Team Improvement</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;retrospectives---a-tool-for-team-improvement&quot;&gt;Retrospectives - A Tool for Team Improvement&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One way of improving a software development team is to regularly hold retrospectives (or ‘retros’ for short). A retrospective is an exercise where a team sets aside a timeboxed amount of time (typically one hour) and looks back on previous times, discussing what went well, what problems could have been avoided, and what could have been done better. Retrospectives are an opportunity to identify and discuss problems, as well as introduce ideas to make the team better. Retrospectives work best when performed in consistent intervals, whether it be every week, every month, or every project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;who-should-attend-the-retro&quot;&gt;Who Should Attend the Retro?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Typically, when it comes to who attends a retro, smaller groups of people are better. Speaking from personal experience, I have been in several retros involving large groups of people (sometimes as large as the entire office!) and they were DISASTERS. With large groups of people, retros tend to go for much longer than intended. People get tired and lose focus. Conversations that occur in the retro may be of interest to only a small percentage of the people in attendance, leading to people messing around on their phones and not paying attention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of the developers on the team should attend. If the office has tens of developers who work on smaller feature teams, then the developers on those feature teams should attend. Any BAs or QAs who work directly with the developers should be there as well. Managers and bosses should not attend. Their presence may cause people to not be totally honest about how they feel for fear of some type of retribution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ideally, an impartial third party should be the moderator of the retro. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Retro attendance should not be mandatory. If anyone on the team feels like retrospectives do not bring value, or if the person feels like their time will not be effectively spent in the retro, they should not be forced to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;where-should-the-retro-be-held&quot;&gt;Where Should the Retro Be Held?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A room large enough to comfortably hold all of the people attending the retro should be used. There should also be a whiteboard available. The whiteboard will host the data provided by those attending the retro. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-materials-are-required&quot;&gt;What materials are required?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Writing utensils, such as markers or pens, are necessary. Index cards and Post-its are great, especially if there are multiple colors. Many retro exercises make use of different colored paper in one form or another. The moderator may want a timer to make sure things don’t run too long. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;how-long-should-the-retro-be&quot;&gt;How long should the retro be?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An hour should be sufficient for retro. How that hour should be allocated will be elaborated on shortly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-flow-of-a-typical-retrospective&quot;&gt;The Flow of A Typical Retrospective&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A typical retrospective can be divided into several phases:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Set the stage - 5 minutes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gather data - 10 minutes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Generate insights - 20 minutes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Decide what to do - 20 minutes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Close the retrospective - 5 minutes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The times I have specified above are not absolute. Feel free to tweak these values to make them fit better for your retros. This is an example of what a retro might be for a small team. Larger teams will obviously require more time. Longer retros should have breaks interspersed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;set-the-stage&quot;&gt;Set the stage&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the start of the retro, the moderator should thank everyone for coming. The fact that people are attending alone shows that the people in the room have a desire to make a better team. The moderator should explain the purpose of the retro, as well as the schedule, for any people who are unfamiliar with how a retro works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tell the team that the purpose of the retro is not to blame anyone. Read them the &lt;a href=&quot;http://retrospectivewiki.org/index.php?title=The_Prime_Directive&quot;&gt;Prime Directive&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Regardless of what we discover, we understand and truly believe that everyone did the best job they could, given what they knew at the time, their skills and abilities, the resources available, and the situation at hand.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remind them that this is an opportunity to learn and get better, not to blame.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One exercise that I like to do is an ice-breaker. I pose a simple question that asks for a short answer to everyone in the room. An example would be ‘In a few words, how do you feel the last week went?’ The objective is to get everyone to start talking. Once they start talking by answering a simple question such as this, they will be more prone to engage in conversation throughout the retro. This exercise also gives a reading about how the team feels in general.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;gather-data&quot;&gt;Gather data&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next phase in the retro is where members of the team provide data about the period of time the retro is focused on. There are a number of exercises that can be done to collect data. Some of my gotos are Mad Sad Glad, and 4 L’s (Liked, Lacked, Learned, Longed For). These types of exercises allow the group to generate data from multiple emotions and mindsets, providing a comprehensive picture. It’s best if this data is placed in an area where everyone in the room can look at it, such as on a whiteboard. Different colored index cards or post-its help with associating with different emotions (red for mad, blue for sad, etc.).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;generate-insights&quot;&gt;Generate insights&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once data has been collected, that data can tell a story. One way of generating insights is by mute mapping. Allow 10 or so minutes for everyone to go up to the board and group data that they think are related. After these groups are formed, circle them or box them to signify that they are grouped together. Try to come up with themes for each group. Allow the team members to vote for one or two topics to talk about. Let the team discuss the topic(s) in detail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;decide-what-to-do&quot;&gt;Decide what to do&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, there should have been discussion about the time period the retro is focused on. Team members should have some ideas of things they want to do (or keep doing) to make things better. I recommend steering the team toward making SMART goals. SMART is an acronym.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Specific&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Measurable&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Attainable&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Relevant&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Timely&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SMART goals are concrete and are easy to see if they have been met or not after a specified period of time. They are also realistic. Have the team come up with two or three smart goals. Place them somewhere everyone can easily see them so that the goals are not easily forgotten about. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;close-the-retrospective&quot;&gt;Close the retrospective&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;End the retrospective by retro’ing the retro. Ask the team for feedback. What was good? What was bad? What was missing? Tell the team that you welcome any feedback they want to give you, whether it be in public or private.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, thank everyone for investing their time in coming to the retro.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Retrospectives are a great way for a software development team to identify problems and look for ways to improve. If you want a great resource on retrospectives, check out &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Agile-Retrospectives-Making-Teams-Great/dp/0977616649&quot;&gt;Agile Retrospectives - Making Good Teams Great&lt;/a&gt;. Pretty much everything I talked about in this post (and more!) can be found in this book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;resources&quot;&gt;Resources&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Agile-Retrospectives-Making-Teams-Great/dp/0977616649&quot;&gt;Agile Retrospectives - Making Good Teams Great&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://retrospectivewiki.org/index.php?title=The_Prime_Directive&quot;&gt;Prime Directive&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 27 Mar 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://blog.chriszimmerman.net//2015/03/27/Retrospectives.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.chriszimmerman.net//2015/03/27/Retrospectives.html</guid>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
